Guide to the Blanche Meyer Collection of Jean Giono
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Blanche Meyer collection of Jean Giono
1938-1974
GEN MSS 457
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.19
(12 boxes)
Correspondence consists principally of letters from Jean Giono to Blanche Meyer, along with several to her husband, Louis. The Manuscripts include notebooks and drafts of "Pour Saluer Melville", and "Faust au Village". Among the Other Papers are a group of letters from publishers requesting rights to Giono's works, clippings about Giono's life and work, and a number of photographs of Giono in his native Provence.
Meyer, Blanche, 1908-1988
Giono, Jean, 1895-1970 ( Faust au village)
Giono, Jean, 1895-1970 ( Pour saluer Melville)
Giono, Jean, 1895-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Blanche Meyer on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1974-75.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Jean Giono Collection, GEN MSS 458
JEAN GIONO (1895-1970)
Jean Giono, French novelist, whose works told stories of the people of his native Provence, coupled with a celebration of nature. They include Le hussard sur le toit and Deux cavaliers de l'orage. He died in his native village of Manosque in October 1970.
Scope and Contents
The Blanche Meyer Collection of Jean Giono consists of letters, manuscripts, clippings, and photographs which document the work of the French novelist, Jean Giono, especially as they involved his relationship with Blanche Meyer. The collection has been organized into three series: Correspondence, Manuscripts, and Other Papers and span the years 1938-1974.
Series I, Correspondence, consists primarily of letters from Giono to Blanche and Louis Meyer between 1939-1969. The majority is addressed to Blanche, with several letters to other persons present, most likely enclosures in letters to Blanche Meyer. [A list of these other letters in included in the box and folder list.] Envelopes are files separately from the letters (as they were received with the collection).
Series II. Manuscripts, includes original drafts for several Giono items, including notebooks for "Pour saluer Melville" and a holograph copy of "Faust au Village". Several shorter items, including two untitled pieces are also found here. One other manuscript is present, an essay on Giono by a American student.
Series III, Other Papers, contains documentary material about Giono's life and career. The Publication and Permissions Files concern requests to use works by Giono, mostly addressed to Blanche Meyer, as owner of certain copyrights. Also present here are several contracts concerning Giono works and a legal brief addressing a dispute between Giono and Marcel Pagnol. The Clippings encompass reviews and mentions of Giono, obituaries and tributes to Giono, and a small group of essays by Giono. Following a single item of Printed Material, a book prospectus for "Provence", are a number of finely printed photographs, showing Giono in and around the landscape of Manosque, many carrying a photographer's stamp, "Karquel". Included at the end of this series are original wrappers received with the collection.
Box 12 contains Oversize items from Series III.
Novelists, French -- 20th Century; Giono, Jean, 1895-1970; Meyer, Blanche, 1908-1988
- Correspondence, 1938-70; Series I; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically.
  - "Cataloger's" chronological listing of letters, annotated, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Cataloger's" notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes list of letters previously classified apart, as "le dossier vert"
  - Ferroud, Jolaine, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    (several letters are photocopies only)
  - Meyer, Blanche and Louis, 1939-44 (Box 2, Folder 4-10)
    Includes: letter to JG from Alice Cocéa, 1944 Apr; Letter from BM to her sister, 1944 Oct 18; letter from J. Rigoir to BM, 1944 Nov 14; and several fan letters to JG
  - Meyer, Blanche and Louis, 1945-50 (Box 3, Folder 11-17)
    Includes: letter from JG to Madame Bravay, [1949] Oct (photocopy); letter from Oswald Baudot to JG, 1950 Feb 27 [photocopy]; letter from JG to Anna Pobin, [1950 May]; and letter from JG to "Jolaine", [1950 Sep]
  - Meyer, Blanche and Louis, 1951-70 (Box 4, Folder 18-31)
    Includes: letter from BM to JG, 1954 Jan 1 (carbon)
  - Envelopes for letters to Blanche and Louis Meyer, 1939-49 (Box 5, Folder 32-41)
  - Envelopes for letters to Blanche and Louis Meyer, 1950-69 (Box 6, Folder 42-51)
- Manuscripts, 1939-51, n.d.; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II, Writings, is arranged alphabetically by author and title.
  - GIONO, JEAN
    - "Accompagné de la flûte: Poêmes"
      - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 53)
      - Typescript carbon, "collationné", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - "Faust au Village"
      - "Cataloger's" notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 55)
      - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 56)
      - Typescript, photocopy, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - "L'histoire de Monsieur Jules"
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - "Pour saluer Melville"
      - "Cataloger's" notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 59)
      - Notebooks, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 60-61)
      - Holograph, corrected, 1939-40 (Box 7, Folder 62)
      - Page proofs, bound, corrected, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - "Préface pour Le marin de haute mer"
      - Typescript carbon, 1950 Mar 1 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - "La route des vins: Préface"
      - Typescript, mimeograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - "Le temps des prisons"
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, 1951 Jan (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - "Le Voyage en calèche"
      - "Cataloger's notes", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 67)
      - Holograph fragment, 1947 Sep 20 (Box 7, Folder 68)
        Includes letter to Blanche Meyer, n.d.
    - Untitled: "Je suis très sensible au charme des étoffes.. ."
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, 1948 Apr 21 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Untitled: "Une Lombarde d'Andes nommée Magia Polla. .."
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Untitled: Note removed from Blanche Meyer's copy of Naissance de l'Odysse
      - Holograph, 1943 Mar 10 (Box 7, Folder 70a)
  - RISLER, CHANTAL
    - "Orchestration sur le 'Chant du Monde'"
      - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 71)
        Includes letter from Germaine Brée to JG
- Other Papers, 1941-74, n.d.; Series III; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Series III, Other Papers, is listed by type of material.
  - PUBLICATION AND PERMISSIONS FILES
    - "Cataloger's" notes
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Les amis de L'originale
      - Correspondence, 1950 Nov 17 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - L'Arche, Editeur
      - Correspondence, 1950 Jan 17 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Denise Clairouin, Bureau litteraire
      - Correpondence and contracts, 1949-51 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Georges Dechalotte
      - Correspondence and contracts, 1947-49 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Imprimerie Pierre Faulac
      - Correspondence, 1950 Mar 9 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Gallimard, Librairie
      - Correspondence and contracts, 1947-49 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Gallimard, Editions
      - Contract, 1972 Jul 4 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Jean Garganoff
      - Contract, [1941] (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Aline Giono - Blanche Meyer
      - Contract, 1972 Jul 21 (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Jean Giono - Blanche Meyer
      - Contract, 1950 Mar (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Ides et Calendes
      - Correspondence, 1949-50 (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Marcel Pagnol
      - Legal brief, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Georges Roche
      - Correspondence, 1949-50 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Les Éditions Vialétay
      - Correspondence, 1949-50 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - René Zimmermann
      - Correspondence, 1950-51 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - CLIPPINGS
    - Writings by Jean Giono, 1939-70 (Box 8, Folder 88)
      Includes: "L'art de vivre", 1970 Oct 13; "Possession du monde", 1942 Mar 14; Excerpt from "Pour saluer Melville", n.d.; and "Recherche de la pureté", 1939 Aug 4
    - Obituary and tributes to Jean Giono, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Reviews of works by and mentions of Jean Giono, ca. 1940-74 (Box 8, Folder 90-93)
  - PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Book Prospectus for "Provence", n.d. (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Jean Giono in Manosque countryside, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 95)
      by Karquel
    - Jean Giono in his office, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 96-97)
    - Jean Giono in his office, and looking at portrait of himself (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Jean Giono with his daughter, Sylvie, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 99)
    - Jean Giono with Blanche Meyer at Col du Chat, 1943 Jul (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - Jean Giono and Blanche Meyer at Saint Maurice en Trièves, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Jean Giono with Blanche and Louis Meyer, Lucien Jacques, and Madame Bernard at Blanche Meyer's house, Manosque, [ca. 1942] (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Jean Giono with Louis and Maggie Vaudable, Inez Lemonnier, and Jolaine P.O. Ferroud at La Croix, Valmes, [ca. 1945] (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Jean Giono with motion picture cameramen in Manosque countryside, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Jean Giono with shepherds and sheep in Manosque countryside (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Jean Giono - candids (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Blanche Meyer - portraits by Lipnitzki, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Drawing of Blanche Meyer's house in Manosque, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Triptych of frescos by Lucien Jacques in Blanche Meyer's house, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Manosque countryside, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - WRAPPERS
    - Original wrappers recieved with collection, n.d. (Box 9)
    - Original wrappers recieved with collection, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Original wrappers recieved with collection, n.d. (Box 11)
- OVERSIZE, 1939-74; 2; (1 box)
  - Clippings - Writings by Jean Giono (in Series III), 1939-70 (Box 12, Folder 111)
  - Clippings - Obituary and tributes to Jean Giono (in Series III), 1970 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - Reviews of works by and mentions of Jean Giono (in Series III), ca. 1940-74 (Box 12, Folder 113)